[Music]
welcome to this business Central launch
event for the 2023 release Wave 2 where
in this session we're going to talk
about what's new in powerbi and
Reporting for developers my name is
Kenny ponan I'm a program manager on the
product team and with me today I have a
very special guest hello my name is ero
I'm a software engineer in the business
Central team that manages Integrations
including the one with
powerbi and you'll see more about that
in a few
minutes in this session we're going to
talk about how the world is changing not
everything but with
analytics we talk about power in beted
lots of new cool stuff Happening Here we
talk about data analysis on queries um a
new feature that is even not yet in the
release notes but we wanted to show you
multi worksheet data and Excel layouts
talk about teaching tips and help T like
making reports and queries discoverable
and easy to understand and finish up
with some learning resources and
Goos so let's get started
the world is changing that's a dramatic
thing and it is really dramatic but it's
kind of let's focus a little bit here on
reporting in business Central so here
things are changing but reporting in
business Central means actually
traditionally three things analytical
reports processing only reports where
you just use the request page as
something to to get some input from the
user and printable documents such as
invoices documents that needs to go to a
PDF in this session we're just going to
talk about the analytical reports
okay now within
organizations different roles in that
organization typically have different
needs for analytics and I say typical
many times on this slide because of
course if you are working in the
leadership team you might also need to
do ad hoc analysis and so on right but
typically when you go up the
organizational hierarchy you also have a
need to aggregate data simply because
you you need to lose some detail to get
the bigger picture similar in when you
work on the actual business processes
the the aggregation up to a kpi might be
losing too much detail so typical ways
to consume data is when you work on the
actual business processes you need
something that is operational likely to
be on screen related to your task when
you work in middle management you
typically need some cated reports as
well as ability to do ad hoc analysis
and when you move up to the leadership
roles this is where kpis dashboards
Financial reports is what you need So
based on
this understanding in of analytics in
different customer organizations we put
together a vision on how we want this
analytical reporting story uh for
business Central and we came up with the
overall Vision that this has to be for
online consumption not print right now
that's the way reporting works right we
go to a request page we get a PDF and if
we want a different set of data we run
the report Rec again to get a different
PDF let's not do that anymore so we came
up with three
different uh road maps or part of this
journey the first is consuming data we
need or we want Core Business scenarios
for business Central to have outof thee
boox reporting analytics Simply Built in
so no need to get additional developers
or or buy solutions to do your core
business scenarios analytics on those
number two most analytics um users need
can be covered with no code or low code
Solutions and three we want enable to
enable customers with easy access to
data for advanced power bi and analytics
and of course in the spirit of business
Central isvs as well as as Microsoft as
part of the core product should be it
should be possible to deliver analytics
Solutions uh with apps or perent
extensions and just highlighting one sec
more there's of course in reporting also
something we call document reporting
this is not part of this presentation
okay so let's start with new powerbi
embed capabilities for the AL developer
because you here in this session because
you're a developer and en R let's hear
about the new capab ities thanks Kenny
so let's talk about what you as a
developer can achieve with a powerbi
embed with a business Central release
wave have 2
2023 uh so we want to highlight some
points on what you can do so first of
all you can open a report in expanded
mode directly using an Al action for
example so the user can use all the real
estate on screen you can also um prevent
the user from changing which report is
shown in a certain context inside
business Central and also so you can
enable them or prevent them from
changing the report page um also we are
taking advantage of the new powerbi
scorecards which were uh released in the
last few months and now you can also
embed them in business Central and see
them as if they were any other powerbi
report or dashboard so can I ask you
something yeah for the for the first of
all for the middle
one this actually means like prior to
this power be beted was maybe more
thought of as an end use experience
where end users would embed their things
but it seems to me with this isvs Al
developers can now control like
delivering powerbi content with their
apps is that kind of is how how you see
it as well yes that's correct so um you
in some pages the partner will know
which report makes sense to show and it
doesn't make sense to clutter the user
experience with a lot of actions and
selections because for example that's
just one report you as an IV want to
show for example in your own alp page or
also in a business Central built-in page
um so it has definitely a much more
developer Focus from this wave really
nice so and then for the for the powerp
metrics
so this
is this is part of what we hope with
this no code experience for the vision
right with with scorecards and with
metrics as long as you have kpis defined
in powerbi end users can now set up
scorecard s point to the business kpis
they want to track and just use out of
the box no code experience for powerbi
with metrics to track their business
that's correct and that's very powerful
because of course the metrics can come
directly from business Central or from
some other system that you might have uh
inside Microsoft or external as long as
you can get the data to parbi you can
build your own kpi and show it within BC
very nice let's see how it works so
let's talk about code how do we achieve
this first of all let's talk about how
you embed a report in uh expanded mode
directly so uh we have this record which
is powerbi displayed element and you can
just set the element type in my example
here a report you can just add the
report ID and the report embed URL this
information is available from the
powerbi rest apis so you can get them
directly from your code or in case you
want a specific report to be shown you
can of course hardcode them directly um
and then you can just spin this parbi
element card page which is going to
display the report in full page we'll
see that in a minute I just want to
mention the other capabilities that I
had in the previous slce so um for
example you can have the show pains in
expanded mode and show pains in normal
mode Flags these are controlling whether
the user can change the report page and
can change the report filters while
viewing a report you can also just have
a report open on a specific report page
in case you have a multipage report
that's also new
capability and last but not least if you
want the user to not change the report
shown in a page so um no this is not
about changing the report page but
changing which report is displayed you
can set this flag lock to selected
element to T but of course this is a lot
of code in slid in slides so I'll just
move to show you how it works in reality
last transition to my visual studio code
I have my perent extension and um for
example in my example I want to add a
powerbi report on a fact box for the
chart of accounts this is one of the
pages where we don't provide a report or
a part out of the box inside business
Central but you as a partner can add it
just with a few lines of Al code you can
see here the
example and this is just how to set the
what we call context for a part but then
you need to tell the AL code which
report you want to show for this
specific context and in my case I'm
doing this as part of the on open page
trick triigger but you as a partner
might have a more complicated Logic for
this as you can see just as I showed you
in the slide earlier you just need to
set um basically four Flags so the
element type the element ID and the
element embed URL you also need the
context which is basically the
identifier of where these reports will
be shown it needs to be in my case the
same string as the one I had um further
on top of the page for the powerbi part
so let's just publish my
extension and let's
see how it works in reality so this is
my chart of accounts page and you can
see on the right that I successfully
embedded the powerbi report in business
Central on the fact box now um you might
see that um in in this particular view
the report is quite small but we'll
actually address that later first what I
want to show you is the actions we
talked about so here for example the
user can select a different report or if
they have multiple report enabled for
this particular view they can jump to
the previous and next
one but as a partner let's say I don't
want that to happen I can just lock um
to the selected element and now I can
just update my
extension and now if I refresh the page
you'll just see these actions are
completely gone so this enables you as a
partner to prevent the user from Ming up
with the powerbi setup yeah because you
say messing up here it could be that
user is experimenting and
suddenly is she or he cannot go back to
the original intent so here you're
actually just guiding the content saying
it's should be this and you cannot by
mistake get out of this context that's
correct so you might the user might just
get the wrong report displayed here um
or the wrong set of reports or it might
also just select no reports so they just
see the initial screen and we of course
want to avoid these um and give you
developers the option to let's say
railroad the user into getting just the
reports you want to show them
MH but um as I mentioned earlier there's
here this report um is the one we
actually have as out of the box with
business Central but uh it has two
report pages but here you can see only
one page which is the one with the um
nicer graphs if you want but let's say
that you as a partner want to point this
report to a different
page well you can do that by just
setting the report page value in my case
this is the name of the other page that
you couldn't see until now and let's say
I also want to show the page selection
so that the user can jump back and forth
to different report pages so I will just
enable these three
flags and you will see that now my
report is going to point to a different
page which has just a column chart and
now I will be able to jump to the other
page which is the one we saw earlier and
just back and forth as a user to
whichever page I need this
also affects the pains in expanded mode
so here you can see that I have the
filters for example pain open so if my
report has any filter from here I'll be
able to tweak them just to see whichever
data I need in my case this report
doesn't have any filter set so there
just no option for me but if there were
um this is also guarded by the flag that
I set in the AL
code but now as we mentioned earlier um
this report is actually pretty small
here and in this context maybe I'm very
interested to only one of these pie
charts so it would be very nice if I as
a developer could zoom into one of these
pie charts and just make sure that's the
only one that the user can see that's
also a new function functionality that
is available from the current
wave so instead you can
have a report
visual as you can see here I am just
changing the element type to be report
Visual and then I am adding some
additional parameters for the rep visual
key in this case I will need the page ID
and the visual ID for the rest
everything is exactly as you saw it
before so let's publish this extension
and see how my single pie chart will
look like on the chart of account fact
boox and as you can see now I only see
my pie chart in this case of course the
report is not very relevant because the
top five customers might not fit that
well with a chart of accounts um but
that's exactly why we need you as a
developers because you have the
knowledge and the capacity to just get
the customer exactly the reports they
need can I say something here of course
so what you saw saw in Riku was
traversing the like visual hierarchy
inside powerbi artifacts on the top
level you have a report a report
consists of multiple Pages actually
think the different like the tabs you
showed is also new in the visualization
yes right the ability to if you embed
the report you can go through the
different pages and on a particular page
uh you can have multiple visuals and
even you can seems like we can even
point to a particular visual inside a
report so full flexibility into that
hierarchy of visuals now available for
for developers um and maybe you should
start learning a little bit of powerbi
it seems like this is going into the
space of development that's absolutely
correct but talking about hierarchy of
things you can display inside business
Central now we haven't yet shown any
scorecard oh yeah so I have now created
a demo action which I will call open Q2
goals expanded and uh let's say for
example that I have my scorecard which
just tracks my most important goals for
the current um quarter I can just embed
it inside business Central here we also
added an action full screen so in this
case my screen is zoomed in for this
demo but if you want to see just the the
scorecard in a more expanded mode you
can also get to full screen using the
action as a user and this is just
achieved by what I showed you earlier in
the slides but I will also show you
again here you can just set in my case a
temporary record with a powerbi
displayed element and as we saw earlier
you just need to specify the type in
this case powerbi recognizes scorecards
as reports so you have to set it as
report and then you need the scorecard
key and the invite URL that's all you
need to achieve what I just show
you pretty cool I think hopefully this
will get you more interested in in
powerbi development and integrating with
with a because now you can you can make
powerbi a seamless experience with your
apps maybe as a VAR you could start
deploying pendant extensions then add
that add this nice embed experience for
the customer to have both something that
demos nice in a pre-sales but even more
importantly for go live that you
actually embed the reporting experience
directly into business Central love it
that's very correct love it I'll give it
back to you Ken you thank you for the
next section
perfect okay so low code no codes
powerbi metrics directly edable inside
business Central using ale let's switch
gears a little bit but not too much in
this wave we added the ability to do
data analysis not only on list pages but
directly on on query
objects query objects have been in the
product for a long time but never with
the strong UI uh for analysis that we
have that we are adding
now for I mean you you could always just
do uh SL question mark query equals a
query object and then you would see kind
of a list page on the query
but that's not really what queries are
for queries are for analyzing mocking up
data joining data that's that's where
where queries are really useful and
until now it was mainly used for
performance tuning but not anymore
there's now a new this new analysis
toggle uh button on uh on on a query and
uh we also added support for run
objects so for instance you can add an
action on a page extension doesn't have
to be on a page it could also be your
own but let's let's say you want to have
a new nice way to analyze item by
location and we you you build a
fantastic query that joins item with
location and other tables and make that
available then directly in on the items
lists um I'm adding a new um analyze
items action that simply runs the query
the query is called item hero query
because it a hero query for item and you
can see here in the UI how it is
embedded directly um as an action so the
user doesn't really know it's a it's a
query for them it's just part of the
report uh on the page so let's see how
that how such a data mockup looks with
an IUI on
top so here I'm um I'm working with in
inventory I'm on the items list page and
look my very nice developer added a
query here I don't know if it's a query
but you know because you just saw the
code previous code it's called analyze
item Ledger and if I go
here I actually have complete data
analysis slice and Di experience now on
queries um everything works as expected
you can rename you can have additional
and analysis tabs in this particular
example I'm slicing or grouping item
description uh by location but it's not
location code as the one you saw or you
you know from the list this is a mockup
of the data from the items list page or
the items um table and then joined with
the location um table and you can see
here for the Mexico swivel chair that we
are using
the warehouse names and not the the
codes and if I even want you can see
them down here if I even want the cities
I can just drag them in here and if we
go for Mexico now you can see East
Warehouse is in Atlanta so this allows
me as a user to
Simply slice and dice the data
that how it should be not necessarily
only these like code names and weird
things that that is in in displayed on
the lists but but the the names and the
things that I I really care about and
all the other things pivot grouping so
on all of this works is just based on a
query and not a list
page so as a developer
now maybe you should think about what
are the queries you can build bring to
your users and then they will kind of do
the report recording and things out of
the box so the only thing that is code
here is the data mash up and then you
you can unblock the users to to do their
ad hoc analysis or data or
reporting speaking of exactly this
between low code and no code this is
this is also the area of excel layouts
we added Excel layouts a year ago as a
way for end users
to both use Excel for the layout
experience with no or low code and also
for consuming the data now what the the
the previous layout feature didn't
handle parent child or overview detailed
data types very well um so that meant
for if you want to do excel layouts in
the past for these types of data it
would be very Compass some in the in the
Excel um the way you you develop your
Excel layouts well not anymore with this
uh change with this wave we adding a way
for you to Simply have multiple
worksheets in your report in your Excel
and then that just leans so much more
into the way you model things in Excel
let me show you what this means so on
the report object as a developer you now
have a
new property called Excel layout
multiple data sheets and if you set that
to true you go from a model where you
have one worksheet with these null you
can see all these areas of nulls um and
each of these columns here would be a
different uh data item whereas in the
new model you just have one data tab or
worksheet for each data item
right what this allows you to do is
first of all much EAS easier integration
to power query inside Excel so you can
kind of model on top of these different
worksheets and enrich the data maybe
have computed columns rename things
whatever you like in power query as well
as then adding the other power element
in Excel which is power pivot power
pivot allows you to then model
relationships between these so in this
example you can
see the value entry customers and items
are three different data items in the
report objects they then get their own
table inside with power query and then
with power pivot um we Define
relationships between them to create a
really powerful interactive report in in
Excel what I think will happen with this
is once this takes off is that end users
will also start of start working a
little bit more with power query and
modeling and in the same kind of tools
that are the same ones as in EN ru's
world with with power power Pi
powerquery is the same language the same
experience both in Excel and in power pi
and I think maybe this could also help
the transition uh even maybe even for
end users from Excel into powerbi but
let's
see the only thing you need to do as a
developer is when you create your data
sets is just one property Excel layout
multiple data sheets set it to true and
uh and and this whole new experience
unlocks in
Excel but it doesn't matter if we create
nice content if users cannot find it
right and if they don't understand it
like we would never put in functionality
into business Central without any
explanation and documentation what is
this for and how do I use it why is why
shouldn't it be the same with the with
report objects and queries so teaching
tips is now available on queries and on
reports and um as well as context
specific help so it works just the same
as what you would expect with
um uh on
pages so in code it's the same thing on
request page for report you add about
title about text and context sensitive
Health page just like you would do on a
page and look it just works teaching tip
directly on the request page if you
click show help you would get the same
information in the help Pane and the
context sensitive help page will now if
you set it it will now show up in help
and you would just provide the normal
exper guided experience for your reports
and your queries um as you would on
pages for CES exact same thing about
title about text context sensitive he
page and a new kit on the Block usage
category for for queries if you set this
to reports and Analysis at least uh in
23 um version
23.1 it will also show up in uh in help
me in in sorry in tell me help and in
report
Explorer um same thing here for queries
you get these context specific help and
you get the teaching
tips so how do you consume all this do
we have any resources to help you out
yes first of all power Pi do you want to
talk a little bit about what we offer in
docs for powerbi uh for helping powerbi
and Ale developers yeah of course so uh
first of all I want to mention that the
code that I showed you earlier is for
the major part available on the BCT Tech
Reaper which you can find at aka. m s
/bc you can also find documentation on
how to handle these different parameters
in our parbi documentation but what I
mean if you're an Al developer and like
what's this powerbi thing how do I get
started we have all been there I've been
here and R like new world what do I do
there are excellent learning paths for
powerbi right there on docs free of char
like it doesn't cost you anything except
your time so spend a few minut 10
minutes every morning learn how start
learning this new world and I think you
will make something that is going to be
great for your
customers for reporting specifically for
Excel and the things you see here we
also updating the current documentation
actually including also ways to make
your report layouts resilient to
failures as well as your reports so that
the reporting experience you give as an
isv um will just be much better for um
for your customers we have Excel samples
so aka.ms slbc Excel samples this is
where you get guidance on how do you
define good data sets how do you define
good layouts different techniques in
Excel there are many different things
you haven't seen before I'm pretty sure
table formulas Dynamic arrays power
query how do I do this well I have some
guidance for you here video from the
community if you want to learn like that
if you want to do presentations for
events or conference internally
externally there's a powerp PowerPoint
deck for you here just download and and
take it from there and there's an FAQ
for everything you might want to ask but
didn't uh they were afraid to um as well
as what enrio mentioned powerbi
samples so you have uh enrio has added
really nice code samples here for again
BC PBI powerbi samples and that's
available with code samples that you can
just take down and start using tomorrow
and they should be quite clearly
commented in case you don't remember
exactly what the parameter does you
should find the code comment in the
source
code so to
conclude the world is changing for a
developers in the context of
analytics so next time when the customer
asks can you build me a report don't ask
oh sure how would you like like the
these columns and how should it printed
in like don't do that instead ask the
customer what is it that you need and
and for what and and for when and so on
and only then choose which technology
should be used think about that triangle
and the
organization maybe it will be in enri
world of powerbi Ed right or it could be
in the build a query or have a maybe
there's even a list page that offers
this so that buil-in data analysis just
works or if it's the case that the the
customer is very proficient in Excel and
or maybe they want Excel just bring like
make them a data set and and let them
care about the layout with Excel so the
Goos
most important thing understand the
customers analytical requirements stop
just developing blindly reports start
supporting their analytical needs so for
powerbi learn how to do it and why do
you want to talk about why that's
important enrio yeah sure um so business
Central is of course an an Erp system
that's where the data is but powerbi the
b in powerbi stands for business
intelligence and where do you get the
business intelligence intelligence from
from the data in business Central so
these two tools are just related with
one another naturally so just go and
learn powerbi powerbi is the Microsoft
tool of choice for business analysis and
in particular for business Central data
and maybe this instead of that's the the
the the top advice here instead of build
me a report it just maybe for the
customer just means build me a query and
then you unlock them a queries are not
just for performance analysis anymore
it's a powerful tool where you can mash
up data give it to the customers they
have ad hoc analysis and self-service
and they have probably going to be fine
with just that a lot of customers a lot
of users might just work with queries
and lists and and uh data analysis
directly there and will never need to
run a report or ever again and finally
for
Excel you need to kind of think of excel
layouts as a different way of reporting
your job as a developer is providing the
data set then the customer Excel Savvy
person who takes over is dealing with
the layout so instead of build me a
report maybe the customer is just asking
build me a report data set and when you
do that I'm pretty sure that some of
your customers who know Excel much more
than you do who live in Excel they will
even learn you a tip or two about Excel
I'm pretty sure of it so other launch
sessions that you might want to do after
this of course if you're here as a
developer what's new in developer tools
that's your one of your main sessions
but
also once you kind of get the feel of
power in uh in in other of the power
tool power automate business events in
data ver so on there's a full session on
that what's new in integration um and
then the third option is the session we
have is for for analyze on on lists and
query but more as a focus from the
functional consultant or the end user so
you might want to augment the developer
focus in this session with a more end
user focus on the LA in the last
session if you want to learn more as
always Yammer is where we have the
in-depth discussions X Twitter are the
small uh for AKA links there's one link
to rule them all BC all if you have
ideas of new functionality or things
that can be improved BC ideas is where
we take you and of course office hours
BC office hours after the launch event
we continue doing office hours where
it's not only content but also q&as and
ways to interact with the product group
these are also recorded and the
recordings are available on that URL so
with that INRI and I would like to say
thank you thank you have a great launch
event